# **DIEGO MANYA GUTIERREZ**

Telephone: (+51) 997461896 E-mail: diego.manyag@gmail.com Web: diegomanya.github.io

Environmental Engineer and Master of Environmental Management with over nine years of professional experience in environmental policy and management in both private and public sector, with emphasis in Latin America and the Caribbean. Specialist in the design and evaluation of environmental strategy, policy and development projects focusing on the use of data science, systems thinking and multidimensional approaches for integrative solutions to relevant environmental and development issues.

### **EDUCATION**

# Yale University, Yale School of the Environment

New Haven, CT, USA

Master of Environmental Management, 2018

- Focus: Data Science for Environmental Policy and Sustainable Development
- Relevant Coursework: International Relations, Environmental Governance and Justice, Urban Planning, Systems Dynamics, Poverty Reduction Economics, Innovation in Government and Society

## Universidad Nacional Agraria La Molina

Lima, PE

Bachelor of Science, Environmental Engineering, 2011 Environmental Engineer, 2015

• Thesis: "Environmental Performance Evaluation of an Environmental Management System in the Port of Callao"

## RELEVANT EXPERIENCE

# United Nations Development Program - Perú

Lima, PE

Technical Coordination Specialist – Integrated Water Resource Management for the

Titicaca, Desaguadero, Poopo, y Salar de Coipasa Binational Project (IWRM – TDPS) March 2019 – December 2022

- Provide strategic advice to the Ministry of Environment on the implementation of the IWRM-TDPS Project and other strategic environmental initiatives including international cooperation, environmental management, and environmental policy.
- Coordinate the technical review, binational negotiations, and provide specialized inputs in the design and development of multiple relevant binational environmental studies and policy proposals including the Transboundary Diagnostic Analysis (TDA), Strategic Action Programme (SAP), and other technical studies in Water Management, Governance, Biodiversity, Natural Infrastructure, Climate Change for the TDPS System and other national initiatives.
- Develop data science and knowledge management analysis and tools with multidimensional information and communication of technical results to relevant stakeholders.
- Facilitate interinstitutional coordination and cooperation in the implementation of the IWRM-TDPS Project's activities, including strategic and technical facilitation of workshops, fostering exchanges, and achieving consensus in technical and strategic issues between multiple actors from Perú and Bolivia.
- Evaluate and support overall planning, management, and implementation for the IWRM-TDPS Project to successfully achieve its technical and financial results (6.2 M USD Project)
- Develop technical briefs and documents related to the performance of the IWRM-TDPS Project and other national strategies and initiatives, including periodic monitoring and evaluation reports for national agencies.
- Review and propose tools and documents for learning and knowledge management based in lessons and outputs of TDPS Project including developing technical summaries and information management.
- Provide oversight on the tasks, activities, and deliverables for project implementation including adaptative management and strategies to deliver expected results.

Remote

Research Associate October 2018 – July 2020

- Contribute and develop research on environmental inequality analysis focused on the distribution of environmental benefits and hazards across population in global cities and in the US.
- Providing statistical and geospatial analysis of environmental and social data of inequality in global cities for the Urban Environment and Social Inclusion Index (UESI) available at <a href="https://datadrivenlab.org/urban">https://datadrivenlab.org/urban</a>
- Support the expansion and liaison with interested cities in the Latin American region.
- Provide trainings and presentation of the results to relevant parties and interested actors.

# United Nations Development Program – LAC Bureau

Remote

Junior Consultant

May 2018-December 2018

- Providing support to national agencies in Latin-American and Caribbean countries in mainstreaming SDG's in their strategic planning through a multidimensional approach and methodological tools. (Rapid Integrated Assessment and COMBOS Approach)
- Providing support to the Regional Bureau of Latin America and the Caribbean in the analysis of development programs and strategies for multiples countries (Mexico, Guyana, Turk and Caicos, Dominican Republic)
- Facilitate virtual and in-person trainings for mainstreaming SDG in national and sectorial policies and cooperation portfolios in Latin-American and Caribbean.
- Support the construction and revision of evidence-based Theory of Change process for the acceleration of SDG's from a multidimensional and systems thinking perspective.
- Prepare tools and training materials for specific training around Sustainable Development Goals and their incorporation in national instruments.

## Yale Data Driven Environmental Solutions Group - Yale FES

New Haven, USA

Graduate Research Assistant

September 2016 - August 2018

- Design and develop new tools to evaluate the environmental performance and inequities of a city for the proof of concept and pilot of the Urban Environment and Social Inclusion Index (UESI) available at <a href="https://datadrivenlab.org/urban">https://datadrivenlab.org/urban</a>
- Develop replicable techniques for advanced data analytics including Big Data and geospatial data
- Participation and facilitation of data analysis workshops, hackatons and presentations related to environmental sustainability and climate change in multiple academic forums
- Writing and editing of chapters and case studies for Pilot Report of the UESI.

### United Nations Development Program – LAC Bureau

New York, USA / Panama City, PA

Graduate Researcher – Sustainable Development Cluster

May 2017-August 2017

- Elaborate a case study report about the use of a new tool for evidence-based policy design that helps to mainstream the Sustainable Development Goals into national and local development priorities.
- Developed a methodological approximation to the integration of socioeconomic and environmental data for analysis of development problems in policy design, particularly for analyzing poverty and environment Linkages.
- Presented at an online course of UNDP Latin America about the use of the tool for environmental problem analysis.

### United Nations Development Program / United Nation Volunteers

Lima, PE

Waste Management Specialist - Poverty and Environment Initiative (PEI) Project

September 2015-July 2016

- Coordinate the update of the National Plan of Solid Waste Management with environmental, social, poverty and gender indicators including technical inputs.
- Review and elaborate monitoring and evaluation reports about the progress of the PEI Project.
- Support the liaison of inter-institutional cooperation between government initiatives and agencies that involve environmental, gender and poverty concerns, including national and municipal institutions.
- Assist in the systematization of experiences and methods of the PEI project to ensure its replication.
- Create and review the operational documents of the PEI Project (\$200,000 Dollars Annual Budget)

**DP World Callao**Lima, PE

Safety and Environment Supervisor

January 2012-September 2015

• Led the critical processes regarding the creation, implementation and certification of the Environmental Management System (EMS) according to ISO 14001 norm.

- Monitoring and Evaluation of Environmental Programs of the organization in different aspects: Environmental Quality, Waste Management, Resource Consumption and Carbon Footprint.
- Design and implementation of Carbon and Energy Accounting systems
- Participation in the certification and monitoring of the EMS from the third-party certifier.
- Identified and verified the compliance of environmental commitments to the Peruvian government
- Support activities related to Corporate Social Responsibility and Sustainability initiatives.
- Direct supervision in routine and non-routine activities in relation to Safety and Environment Standards
- Designed and provided training on Safety and Environment Topics to the staff of the organization.
- Accident Investigations and design of corrective actions.

Safety and Environment Intern

February 2011-January 2012

- Designed and implemented new environmental practices
- Verified the compliance with environmental regulations of the organization
- Training employees in environmental topics

### GRADUATE CONSULTING EXPERIENCE

### Supporting the formulation of the Colombian National Electric Mobility Strategy

United Nations Environmental Program – Regional Office for Latin America and Caribbean

January 2018 – June 2018

Project supporting the work of UNEP and the Move Initiative in Colombia towards the elaboration of a national electric mobility strategy for the country, focusing in the current barriers and possible best practices to successfully promote the adoption of EV in the country.

### Vulnerability Analysis of the Ica River Basin: A Water Risk Analysis from a Livelihoods Perspective

Regional Government of Ica, Ica, Peru

August 2017 - January 2018

Report analyzing the vulnerability of the Ica River Basin to water related natural risks based in the sustainable livelihood's framework. The report included a qualitative and quantitate analysis of the risk of the region including the nature of the risk, the potential impacts to vulnerable communities' livelihoods, the role of the structure of the local government in relation to risks reduction, and recommendations for addressing the topic from a holistic perspective.

# Carbon Offsets and Health Co-Benefits: Assessing the Capacity of the Offset Program to Provide Health Co-benefits to California's Disadvantaged Communities

California Air Resources Board Member, California, United States

January 2017 - May 2017

Report analyzing the existing carbon offset program, part of California's Cap-and-Trade program, to evaluate whether this system can be modified to deliver co-benefits, particularly health co-benefits, to Disadvantaged Communities in California. The report included focused in the governance aspects of the program, highlighting issues around Data Transparency and Community Engagement; as well as analyzing specific Offset Protocols including Urban Forestry, Carbon Farming, Water-Energy Nexus, among others.

### **CONFERENCES AND EVENTS**

# Ciudades Como Vamos 2019 – Lima Como Vamos

Lima, Perú Junio 2019

Presentación del Proyecto Urban Environmental and Social Inclusion Index (UESI) y sus resultados en presentación a actores locales de la ciudad de Lima como parte de Foro Ciudades Como Vamos 2019.

### Resilient Cities 2019 - ICLEI

Bonn, Alemania Junio 2019

Presentación del Proyecto Urban Environmental and Social Inclusion Index (UESI) y sus resultados como parte de panel dirigido a actores locales enfocado a la medición de la sostenibilidad urbana

### United Nations Climate Change Conference 2017 - COP23

Bonn, Germany October 2017

Member of Peru's delegation in COP 23, following negotiations in the topics of Capacity Building, and Technological Framework.

# United Nations Conference on Housing and Sustainable Urban Development - HABITAT III

Quito, Ecuador October 2016

Presented preliminary research about environmental performance measurement and indicator for sustainable cities during side events.

# **PUBLICATIONS**

- Hsu, A., Sheriff, G., Chakraborty, T., & Manya, D. (2021). Disproportionate exposure to urban heat island intensity across major US cities. Nature communications, 12(1), 1-11.
- Hsu, A., Chakraborty, T., Thomas, R., <u>Manya, D.</u>, Weinfurter, A., Chin, N. J. W., ... & Feierman, A. (2020).
  Measuring what matters, where it matters: A spatially explicit Urban Environment and Social Inclusion Index for the Sustainable Development Goals. Frontiers in Sustainable Cities, 2, 62.
- Chakraborty, T., Hsu, A., <u>Manya, D.</u>, & Sheriff, G. (2020). A spatially explicit surface urban heat island database for the United States: characterization, uncertainties, and possible applications. ISPRS Journal of Photogrammetry and Remote Sensing, 168, 74-88.
- Chakraborty, T., Hsu, A., <u>Manya, D.</u>, & Sheriff, G. (2019). Disproportionately higher exposure to urban heat in lower-income neighborhoods: a multi-city perspective. Environmental Research Letters, 14(10), 105003.
- Hsu, A., N. Alexandre, J. Brandt, T. Chakraborty, S. Comess, A. Feierman, T. Huang, S. Janaskie, <u>D. Manya</u>, M. Moroney, N. Moyo, R. Rauber, G. Sherriff, R. Thomas, J. Tong, Y. Xie, A. Weinfurter, Z. Yeo (in alpha order), (2018). 2018 Urban Environment and Social Inclusion Index. New Haven, CT. Yale University.
- Valdivia, S. A. P., & <u>Manya, D.</u> (2017). Análisis del sistema de gestión ambiental de un operador portuario del terminal de contenedores del Puerto del Callao. En Anales Científicos (Vol. 78, No. 2, pp. 148-156). Universidad Nacional Agraria La Molina. (Peer – Review)
- Manya, D., Thomas, R., & Moroney, M. (2017). Urban Environmental Performance Index: The Quito Pilot Case. Available at www.elischolar.yale.edu

### **COURSES AND WORKSHOPS**

Career Essentials in Project Management	Dec 2022
Microsft and Linkdln - Online	
Data Scientist with R	Nov 2022
Datacamp - Online	
Nature Based-Infratructure for Climate Change Adaptation	Oct 2022
International Institute for Sustainable Development (IISD)	
Climate Action for Development for Latin America and the Caribbean	June 2022
Organismo de Estados Americanos (OEA)	
Phyton for Data Science and Machine Learning	Feb 2021
Udemy	
Bienestar más allá del Ingreso	June 2017 – Sept 2017
Programa de las Naciones Unidas para el Desarrollo RBLAC	
Financing for Development	Nov 2015 – Dec 2015
World Bank Group	
Curso de Especialización en Legislación y Política Ambiental	Sept 2015 – Dic 2015
Instituto Científico del Pacífico, Perú	
Greenhouse Gases and Carbon Footprint Training Programme	May 2014
SGS, Lima, Perú	

# **SKILLS**

# Languages

• Proficient in English and Spanish (Native speaker)

# Computer Skills:

- Spatial Analysis ArcGIS, QGIS, Google Earth Engine
- Statistical Analysis: R, Python, Stata, Minitab, Vensim
- Database Management: Excel, SQL